<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>whoami on Dipankar Mazumdar | Data Systems Architecture</title><link>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in whoami on Dipankar Mazumdar | Data Systems Architecture</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Books</title><link>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/books/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/books/</guid><description>Published Works Engineering Lakehouses with Open Table Formats Packt, 2025
A comprehensive guide to building modern data architectures using Apache Iceberg, Hudi, and Delta Lake. This book focuses on architectural patterns, reliability, and performance at scale for the modern data stack.
Apache Iceberg: The Definitive Guide O'Reilly, 2024
The standard industry reference for mastering Apache Iceberg. It covers the internal specifications of the format, snapshot isolation, and how to maintain massive datasets with ease.</description></item><item><title>Research</title><link>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/research/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/research/</guid><description>Published Research Random Forest Similarity Maps: A Scalable Visual Representation for Global and Local Interpretation MDPI Electronics, 2023
This paper explores scalable interpretability techniques for Random Forest models using similarity-based visual representations, enabling both global and local understanding of ensemble decision behavior without sacrificing scalability. Read on MDPI · PDF The Data Lakehouse: Data Warehousing and More arXiv, 2023
This paper examines the evolution of data architectures leading to the lakehouse paradigm—bridging the gap between traditional data warehouses and data lakes—and discusses key system design considerations and trends.</description></item><item><title>Speaking Sessions</title><link>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/speaking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/speaking/</guid><description>Featured Presentations Below are some of my recent sessions covering Apache Iceberg, Hudi, and the Open Lakehouse stack.
Making Lakehouse Table Formats &amp;amp; Catalogs work for you | Data Engineering Open Forum 2025 This talk will go over XTable&amp;rsquo;s architecture and its capabilities, designed to support omnidirectional translation between open table formats. By utilizing shared metadata information, XTable enables continuous metadata translation across these formats, allowing data to be accessed by various compute engines and workflows without duplication or extensive rewrites</description></item><item><title>Writing</title><link>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/writing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dipankarmazumdar.github.io/writing/</guid><description>Featured Technical Blogs Apache Iceberg: Key Innovations So Far An exploration of the core architectural features that made Apache Iceberg an industry standard for open table formats, including snapshot isolation and partition evolution.
Apache Parquet vs. Newer File Formats A technical comparison between the established Parquet format and emerging high-performance alternatives like BtrBlocks and Lance for specialized data workloads.
What is Apache Arrow Flight &amp;amp; ADBC? Breaking down how Arrow Flight and the Arrow Database Connectivity (ADBC) standard are solving the &amp;ldquo;data bottleneck&amp;rdquo; in high-speed analytical systems.</description></item></channel></rss>